white seminary and college student named Jonathan Daniels, from Cambridge, Massachusetts. He and I were both part of a generation of idealistic young people, whose life has been ignited by the freedom fire that ordinary black people were spreading around the nation and throughout the South. We had come to Lowndes County to work in the movement. And it was a nonviolent movement to redeem the souls of America. We believe that everyone, both black and white,
seminarista y estudiante universitario llamado Jonathan Daniels, procedente de Cambridge, en Massachussets. Ambos éramos parte de una generación de jóvenes idealistas cuya vida era encendida por la llama de la libertad que la gente común negra propagaba por toda la nación hasta alcanzar el Sur. Nos desplazamos al condado de Lowndes para trabajar en el movimiento. Era un movimiento pacífico para redimir las almas de EE. UU. Creemos que todos, blancos y negros,
people in the South, could find a redemptive pathway out of the stranglehold of racism that had gripped them for more than 400 years. And on a hot, summer day in August, Jonathan and I joined a demonstration of local young black people, who were protesting the exploitation [of] black sharecroppers by rich land holders who cheated them out of their money. We decided to demonstrate alongside them. And on the morning that we showed up for the demonstration, we were met with a mob of howling white men with baseball bats, shotguns and any weapon that you could imagine. And they were threatening to kill us. And the sheriff, seeing the danger that we faced, arrested us and put us on a garbage truck and took us to the local jail, where we were put in cells with the most inhumane conditions you can imagine. And we were threatened by the jailers with drinking water that came from toilets. We were finally released on the sixth day, without any knowledge, without any forewarning. Just out of the clear blue sky, we were made to leave. And we knew that this was a dangerous sign, because Goodman, Schwerner and Chaney had also been forced to leave jail and were murdered because no one knew what had happened to them. And so, despite our fervent resistance, the sheriff made us leave the jail, and of course, nobody was waiting for us. It was hot, one of those Southern days where you could literally feel the pavement -- the vapor seeping out of the pavement. And the group of about 14 of us selected Jonathan Daniels, Father Morrisroe, who had recently come to the county, Joyce Bailey, a local 17-year-old girl and I to go and get the drinks. When we got to the door, a white man was standing in the doorway with a shotgun, and he said, "Bitch, I'll blow your brains out!" And before I could even react, before I could even process what was going on, Jonathan intentionally pulled my blouse, and I fell back, thinking that I was dead. And in that instant, when I looked up, Jonathan Daniels was standing in the line of fire, and he took the blast, and he saved my life. I was so traumatized and paralyzed by that event, where Tom Coleman deliberately, with malicious intent, killed my beloved friend and colleague, Jonathan Myrick Daniels. On that day, which was one of the most important days in my life, I saw both love and hate coming from two very different white men that represented the best and the worst of white America. So deep was my hurt at seeing Tom Coleman murder Jonathan before my eyes, that I became a silent person, and I did not speak for six months. I finally learned to touch that hurt in me as I became older and began to talk about the Southern freedom movement, and began to connect my stories with the stories of my other colleagues and freedom fighters, who, like me, had faced deadly trauma of racism, and who had lost friends along the way, and who themselves have been beaten and thrown in jail. It is 50 years later. Many people were beaten and thrown in jail. Others were murdered like Jonathan Daniels. And yet, we are still, as a nation, mired down in the quicksand of racism. And everywhere I go around the nation, I see and hear the hurt.
la gente del Sur podía encontrar el camino redentor para liberarse del yugo del racismo que los había dominado durante más de 400 años. Un caluroso día de verano de agosto, Jonathan y yo participamos en una manifestación de jóvenes negros del lugar que protestaban contra la explotación de los aparceros negros por parte de los ricos terratenientes que les engañaban con el dinero. Decidimos manifestarnos con ellos. La mañana de la manifestación, nos encontramos con una turba de hombres blancos que aullaban con bates de béisbol, escopetas y cualquier otra arma que puedan imaginar. Y amenazaban con matarnos. El sheriff, al ver el peligro que corríamos, nos arrestó y nos metió en un camión de la basura para llevarnos a la cárcel local, donde nos encerraron en celdas en las condiciones más inhumanas que se puedan imaginar. Los carceleros nos amenazaban con hacernos beber agua de los retretes. Finalmente nos liberaron al sexto día sin ninguna información ni aviso previo. Como caído del cielo, éramos libres para irnos. Supimos que eso era una señal peligrosa ya que también habían obligado a salir de la cárcel a Goodman, Schwerner y Chaney y fueron asesinados porque nadie sabía qué les había ocurrido. Así, a pesar de nuestra voraz resistencia, el sheriff nos obligó a abandonar la cárcel, y por supuesto, nadie nos esperaba. Hacía calor, era uno de esos días sureños en los que podían sentir en el cemento... el vapor emanando del cemento. Y nuestro grupo de unas 14 personas eligió a Jonathan Daniels, al Padre Morrisroe, recién llegado al condado, a Joyce Bailey, una joven local de 17 años y a mí para ir a comprar bebidas. Al llegar a la puerta, un hombre blanco estaba bajo el marco con una escopeta y gritó: "¡Te voy a volar los sesos, puta!" Antes de que pudiese reaccionar, antes de entender qué ocurría, Jonathan tiró de mi blusa a propósito y caí de espaldas, creyéndome muerta. En ese instante, al levantar la mirada, Jonathan Daniels estaba en la línea de fuego, recibió el balazo y me salvó la vida. Quedé tan traumatizada y paralizada por lo ocurrido, que Tom Coleman, deliberadamente y con mala fe, hubiese asesinado a mi amado amigo y colega, Jonathan Myrick Daniels. Ese día, que fue uno de los más importantes de mi vida, vi tanto el amor como el odio procedentes de dos hombres blancos muy distintos que representaban lo mejor y lo peor de EE.UU. Tan grande era mi dolor por haber visto a Tom Coleman matar a Jonathan ante mis ojos que me volví silenciosa y no hablé durante seis meses. Finalmente, aprendí a tocar esa herida interior al hacerme mayor, y empecé a hablar sobre el movimiento de liberación sureño y a conectar mis relatos con los de otros colegas y luchadores por la libertad quienes como yo, se habían enfrentado al trauma mortal del racismo, habían perdido amigos por el camino y habían sido apaleados y encarcelados. Han pasado 50 años. Muchos fueron apalizados y encarcelados. Otros fueron asesinados como Jonathan Daniels. Y a pesar de eso, como nación estamos todavía hundidos en el lodazal del racismo. Allá donde voy del país, veo y oigo el dolor.
And I ask people everywhere, "Tell me, where does it hurt?" Do you see and feel the hurt that I see and feel? I feel and see the hurt in black and brown people who every day feel the vicious volley of racism and every day have their civil and human rights stripped away. And the people who do this use stereotypes and myths to justify doing it. Everywhere I go, I see and hear women
Y pregunto a la gente, "Dime, ¿dónde duele?" ¿Ven y oyen el dolor que yo veo y siento? Siento y veo el dolor de los negros e hispanos que cada día sufren la carga viciosa del racismo y cada día se ven despojados de sus derechos civiles y humanos. Y la gente que lo hace se vale de mitos y estereotipos para justificarlo. Allá donde voy veo y oigo a mujeres
who speak out against -- who speak out against men who invade our bodies. These same men who then turn around -- the same men who promote racism and then turn around and steal our labor and pay us unequal wages. I hear and feel the hurt of white men at the betrayal by the same powerful white men who tell them that their skin color is their ticket to a good life and power, only to discover, as the circle of whiteness narrows, that their tickets have expired and no longer carry first-class status. Now that we've touched the hurt, we must ask ourselves, "Where does it hurt and what is the source of the hurt?" I propose that we must look deeply into the culture of whiteness. That is a river that drowns out all of our identities and drowns us in false uniformity to protect the status quo. Notice, everybody, I said culture of whiteness, and not white people.
que claman contra... que claman contra los hombres que invaden nuestros cuerpos. Los mismos que se dan la vuelta, los mismos que promueven el racismo y se dan la vuelta y roban nuestro trabajo y nos pagan salarios desiguales. Oigo y siento el dolor de los hombres blancos por la traición de los propios hombres blancos poderosos que afirman que su color de piel es su pasaje a una buena vida y al poder, sólo para descubrir que a medida que se estrecha el círculo de blancura, sus pasajes han caducado y ya no son de primera clase. Ahora que hemos experimentado el dolor, debemos preguntarnos, "¿Dónde duele? y ¿cuál es la causa de dolor?" Propongo que observemos en profundidad la cultura de la blancura. Es el río que ahoga todas nuestras identidades y nos ahoga en una uniformidad falsa para mantener el status quo. Observen todos que he dicho la cultura de la blancura y no la gente blanca.
Because in my estimation,
Porque según mi teoría,
the problem is not white people. Instead, it is the culture of whiteness. And by culture of whiteness, I mean a systemic and organized set of beliefs, values, canonized knowledge and even religion, to maintain a hierarchical, over-and-against power structure based on skin color, against people of color. It is a culture where white people are seen as necessary and friendly insiders, while people of color, especially black people, are seen as dangerous and threatening outsiders, who pose a clear and present danger to the safety and the efficacy
el problema no son los blancos. Es la cultura de la blancura. Y con cultura de la blancura me refiero al grupo de creencias sistemático y organizado, a valores, conocimiento canónico e incluso religión, que mantiene una estructura de poder jerárquica y supremacista basada en el color de la piel en contra de la gente de color. Es una cultura donde los blancos se consideran miembros amigables y necesarios mientras que la gente de color, especialmente los negros, se consideran peligrosos y extraños amenazadores, que suponen un peligro presente y real para la seguridad y la eficacia
of the culture of whiteness. Listen to me and see if you can imagine the culture of whiteness as a dehumanizing process that melts away all of our multiple and interlocking identities,
de la cultura de la blancura. Escúchenme y vean si pueden imaginar la cultura de la blancura como un proceso deshumanizador que deshace nuestras múltiples identidades entrelazadas
such as race, class, gender and sexualities, so that ... so that unity is maintained for power. I believe, because I know and believe that the culture of whiteness is a social construct. Each of us, from birth to death, are socialized in this culture. And it marks people of color also. And it makes people of color, like white people, vote against our interests. Some of you might ask -- and my students always tell me I give hard assignments -- some of you might ask, and rightfully so, "How do we fix this? It seems so all-powerful and overwhelming." I believe that we must fix it, because we cannot humanize our future if we continue to be complicit with the culture of whiteness. Each of us must connect with our authentic selves, with our authentic ethnic selves. And we must connect with the other aspects of our identities. And we must move out of the constructs of whiteness, brownness and blackness to become who we are at our fullest. How do we do this? I believe that we do this through our collective narratives. And our collective narratives must contain our individual stories, the arts, spiritual reflections, literature, and yes, even drumming. (Laughter) It must be a collective telling, because individual stories just create a paradigm where we are pitting one story against another story. These different models that I have talked about tonight I think are essential to providing us a pathway out of the quagmire of racism. And I want to talk about another very important model. And that is redemption. I believe that movements for racial justice must be redemptive rather than punitive. And yes, I believe that we must provide the possibility of redemption for everyone. And we must be willing, despite some of the vitriolic language that might come from those very people who oppress us, I think that we must listen to them
como la raza, la clase, el género y la sexualidad. De manera... de manera que se mantiene la unidad para el poder. Creo, por que lo sé, que la cultura de la blancura es una construcción social. Todos nosotros, del nacimiento a la muerte, socializamos en esta cultura. Y también marca a la gente de color. Y hace que la gente de color, igual que los blancos, voten en contra de nuestros intereses. Algunos se preguntarán... y mis alumnos siempre comentan que las tareas que mando son difíciles, algunos se preguntarán, con toda la razón, "¿Cómo arreglamos esto? Parece todo tan omnipotente y abrumador." Creo que debemos solucionarlo, porque no podemos humanizar el futuro si seguimos siendo cómplices de la cultura de la blancura. Todos debemos conectar con nuestro verdadero yo, con nuestro yo étnico verdadero. Y debemos conectar con los otros aspectos de nuestra identidad. Y debemos escapar de las construcciones de la blancura, la morenez y la negrura para convertirnos en quien somos al máximo. ¿Cómo lo lograremos? Creo que podemos hacerlo a través de la narrativa colectiva. las narrativas colectivas deben incluir nuestras historias personales, las artes, reflexiones espirituales, literatura, y sí, también percusión. (Risas) Debe ser una narrativa colectiva, porque las historias individuales sólo crean un paradigma en el que contraponemos una historia contra otra. Los diferentes modelos de lo que he hablado hoy creo que son esenciales para ofrecernos un camino para salir del cenagal del racismo. Quiero hablar sobre otro modelo muy importante. Se trata de la redención. Creo que los movimientos para la justicia social deben ser redentores en vez de punitivos. Y sí, creo que debemos ofrecer la posibilidad de redención para todos. Y debemos estar dispuestos, a pesar del lenguaje cáustico que pueda venir precisamente de los opresores, pienso que debemos escucharles
and try to figure out where do they hurt. We must do this, I believe, because our redemption is tied into their redemption, And we will not be free until we've all been redeemed from unredemptive anger. The challenge is not easy. And in a technological society, it grows even more complicated, because often we use technologies to perpetuate the very values of racism that we indulge in every day. We use technology to bully, to perpetuate hate speech and to degrade each other's humanities. And so I believe that if we're going to humanize the future, we must design ways to use technology not to degrade us, but to elevate us so that we can live into the fullest of our capacities. And I believe that technology must provide us larger vistas so that we might engage with each other and move beyond the segregated spaces that we live in, every day of our lives. I believe that we can achieve this if we set our minds and hopes on the prize. The question before us tonight is very serious. It is: "Do you want to be healed? Do you want to be healed?" Do you want to become whole and live into all of your identities? Or do you want to continue to cannibalize your multiple identities and privilege one identity over the other? Do you want to join a long line of generations of people who believed in the promise of America and had the faith to upbuild democracy? Do you want to live into the fullest of your potential? I certainly do. And I believe you do, too. Let me just say, quite seriously, I believe in you. And despite everything, I still believe in America. I hope that this offering that I've given to you tonight, that I've shared with you tonight, will provide redemptive pathways so that you might claim the fullest of your identity and become a major participant in humanizing not only the future for yourselves, but also for our democracy. Thank you. (Applause)
y tratar de averiguar dónde les duele. Creo que debemos hacerlo porque nuestra redención está ligada a la suya, y no seremos libres hasta que todos estemos redimidos de una ira sin redención. El desafío no es fácil. Y en una sociedad tecnológica, resulta aún más complejo, porque con frecuencia usamos la tecnología para perpetuar los valores del racismo que permitimos diariamente. Usamos la tecnología para acosar, para perpetuar el discurso del odio y degradar la humanidad ajena. Por eso creo que, si vamos a humanizar el futuro, debemos diseñar maneras de usar la tecnología no para degradarnos, sino para edificarnos y poder vivir al máximo de nuestras capacidades. Y opino que la tecnología debe proporcionarnos horizontes más amplios para poder conectar con los demás e ir más allá de nuestro espacio compartimentado. Creo que podemos lograrlo si centramos la mente y las esperanzas en la recompensa. la pregunta que nos planteamos hoy es muy seria. Es: "¿Quieren curarse?" "¿Quieren curarse?" ¿Quieren sentirse completos y vivir todas sus identidades? ¿O prefieren continuar canibalizando sus múltiples identidades y privilegiar a una por encima de las demás? ¿Quieren formar parte de la larga lista de generaciones de personas que creyeron en la promesa de EE.UU. y tuvieron la fe para construir la democracia? ¿Quieren vivir al máximo de su pontencial? Yo sí, desde luego. Y creo que Uds. también. Déjenme decirles seriamente que creo en Uds. Y a pesar de todo, todavía creo en EE.UU. Espero que el regalo que les he hecho esta noche, que he compartido con Uds. proporcione caminos redentores para que puedan reclamar la plenitud de su identidad y convertirse en participantes principales de la humanización del futuro no sólo para Uds., si no también para nuestra democracia. Gracias. (Aplausos)